Talking my clock. I'm just gonna check to make sure we have a quorum. What's your so are you ready, Linda? I'm all set.
Do we lose Linda?
I'm all set. Oh, okay. Great. All right. So then
it is 07:01 by my computer. It's 08/31/2020.
I'm Megan Lally. I'm going to call the special meeting of the town of Andover's Inland Wetlands and Water Forces Commission to order.
Ask that everybody
please mute themselves.
The commissioners are requested to keep their video on throughout the meeting.
Members of the public, it's optional, though it is preferable if you go to speak to turn your video on just helps
clarify.
So I'm going go ahead and make sure that people who aren't muted and just in case they're walking around their houses I'm going to mute them. Okay,
so believe everyone is on mute.
Okay, so we'll do a quick unmute of the Commissioners in order to do roll call.
All right.
Megan Halley, chair, obviously present. Vice Chairman George Elliott is present.
I see Commissioner
Ed Smith, Commissioner Jim Halsey, and Commissioner Jed Larson. So we have all of our regular commissioners in attendance.
She has not yet been appointed
to
the
commission, but we will be submitting a
recommendation to the board as recommended to do so. But Gabrielle Anderson is also on the meeting today,
listening in.
Don't have any
commentary or voting privileges during this meeting. And then is William
Paul?
Yes. Oh,
I see you. Okay. Great.
Allison's iPad. Got it. Alright.
So mister Monroe has also expressed interest in the commission. I invited him to listen
in on tonight's meeting, so I wanted to check if he was on the line. Okay. So there's no need to cede any alternates. We'll move on to the third item of the agenda, which is the approval of the minutes. All of the commissioners should have received a copy of the 08/03/2020
regular meeting minutes, and they are posted online as well for members of the public to view.
And I will open the floor to any discussion on the minutes.
>> This is Jed on page two, the third paragraph down, second sentence,
a little typo talks about the back property line is not crowded
and it's missing the D.
>> Other
comments on the minutes?
I was not present at the meeting, but I had a comment regarding
page four,
the
line or the first and second line from the top.
It notes that Ms. Puerto is working with her engineer to resubmit a new permit
regarding
the activities at 129 Hebron Road. And I'm just concerned about the language there because the commission has not received
permit or application from that property. So I would recommend that the minutes be revised accordingly.
>> Yes, Commissioner,
Chairman,
Jim Hallessey, did you hear my earlier comment or I was muted?
>> I did not hear your comment. I apologize. Okay. Number
>> 11
indicates that I moved to schedule a special meeting. I believe what I actually did was just point out the action date,
The mandatory action date on the application. This
for
specifically for
12 Webster Lane.
>> That'd be good. Linda, did you get that?
Believe,
I'll, but I believe Jim actually did make the motion.
I'll check the audio on that and if it's incorrect, I'll correct it. Okay.
>> I thought we were waiting for
for request
extension request
extension request from the applicant.
Okay, whatever the audio says is right.
Any further discussion?
>> So back to your comment, Megan, on page four,
was your concern that instead of resubmit a new permit, it was submit a new permit?
Because we haven't actually got one yet?
>> Correct. Yeah, the activities are not permitted by wetlands and we have not received an application yet. So I just didn't want the record to be misleading.
So I not having been present,
if those who are present are in agreement, I would suggest changing the language to to submit an application for a permit.
>> I agree with that based on my recollection from the meeting.
>> Any further discussion on the minutes?
Vice Chairman Elliott or Commissioner Smith, did you have any comments? No.
None.
Hearing Okay. No further discussion, I'll entertain a motion.
>> Mr. Kidd, I make a motion that we approve the minutes from August 3.
>> I'll second. Motion made by Jed Larson,
seconded by George Elliott to approve the August 3 regular minutes
with the corrections noted.
Any additional discussion?
I'll
do a roll call vote.
Vice Chairman Elliott?
Aye.
Commissioner Analisey.
Commissioner Larson.
Aye.
>> Commissioner Smith. Aye.
Chairman McNally will abstain having not been present. So motion carries four zero one.
So that brings us to item four on the agenda permit applications
and
I didn't mention at the beginning of the meeting but those who are unfamiliar with the special meeting
we can't make additions or deletions to the agenda.
We can potentially change the order but just so everyone's clear we can't be adding items
hoping to sit through the meeting and then add something at the end,
I'll stay through the pain.
Okay. So moving on,
item 4A was discussion of application IWWC
twenty-twenty
one submitted by Manuel Correa and Jerry Hardesty for activities at twelve Webster Lane,
a subdivision and new residential construction in an Upland Review area. And I do believe we've had some new materials submitted since our last meeting, which I have asked agent Wagner to present to the commission.
>> Yeah. I had a
letter
from well, I had a new site plan
that show the house rotated
90 degrees.
That was posted
Friday,
I believe.
And then
there was a
a letter dated August 31 from
engineer Brandon Hanfield,
and his evaluation
of
the current
plan.
And then
there's another letter from, Hank Bruner,
also August 31 that has
some recommendations
and
his analysis
of the
current site plan.
That's that's it for the new materials.
>> Do any of the commissioners need a minute to review those materials?
>> What was the question? I have all the materials, I think.
>> I'm hopeful everyone was able to review them in advance of the meeting but did anyone need,
did anyone not receive the materials or need a minute to look at a specific item before we proceed with the discussion?
I received them.
Commissioners, Halsey, Larson, or Elliot?
>> Chairman, did
receive the materials and I have reviewed them.
So is she at
>> policy as well? Have or have not. I'm sorry, I couldn't understand.
Go ahead, Commissioner Larson.
I'm all set.
>> Okay, thank you. Okay, then I'm going to
proceed with discussion on the application. I'll open the floor.
Excuse
me?
Have
>> not seen the letter from Hank Bruner.
I didn't get a copy of this sent to me and I didn't get a copy of the one from the
reviewing
engineer either.
I I read their comments in their minutes, but I haven't seen their letter, and I can't see the bottom of Hank's letter here on my screen.
>> So I'm gonna switch over hopefully to
the town website.
Can you see my screen? Does it have a application submitted pending?
>> No. Because I can't scroll down
for whatever reason. Okay. Letter of confirm.
>> Is it a web right now? Can't see what I think I'm sharing what I'm sharing, but I can't tell.
Website, is it the town's website?
That's what's showing on my screen right now
>> so all materials
received by the commission
posted
to this page under the Associated Application.
So a reference would be for
Agent Wagner to forward materials to the applicant and their
authorized agents as they come in. But you can also always check here. And the information
that's the next discussion item. But the information will be on here. So
go through them. But
items that
agent Wagner just
talked about were the revised site plan. We sent correspondence to you. It was submitted on August 10, but it doesn't have a revision date on it that's different from the previous versions that are submitted. So that's something we want to discuss with you this evening. And then the letter from Hank Bruner
dated the thirty first and the letter from engineer Hanfield also dated the third. I I need to clarify something here,
>> Megan, if I could. The
revised site plan on
08/10
is
not what we are applying for.
That is
to demonstrate
an alternative.
Frankly, my
clients have told me that if that's what you're going to approve, then we might as well just skip the application because that
scenario
doesn't work for them.
>> I don't think that was made clear to the commission.
That was forwarded to us with the understanding that it was a revised site plan. I'm gonna find that out. It
>> is the site plan that will be
it's the site plan that will be submitted to planning and zoning because it meets the subdivision regulations.
All right, but the house turned in that direction and the
driveways and the septic system
are not something that they feel is Okay. Is worth constructing. This I think
>> Alright so
we don't want to see planning and zoning documents. We need to know what materials you're submitting in support of the wetlands application. If there's something that wetlands should not be considering then it should not be presented to wetlands because going to confuse things.
>> Are you there, mister Hardisty? Yes. I am. I yeah. You were you're frozen on my screen, so I didn't hear the the last of what you were saying.
But at
the last meeting Yeah. I'm I'm having trouble.
Can everybody else hear me?
Alice, we can hear you.
I can hear you.
>> At the last meeting, mister Larson
expressed
concern that
that the plans were not consistent, that he was seeing two different plans.
And I I wanted to illustrate that we can show a plan that is
compliant with the subdivision regulations.
But
this is not the plan
that we
expect to that my clients would expect to construct.
The very first set of plans that I submitted that are that have a big preliminary
across the bottom of them, that is the layout that we would propose to construct.
That's the layout that we presented initially.
It's the one that we feel is most appropriate,
and it's the same one that mister Elliott made a motion to approve on the June 1.
>> The map that's on the screen
difficulty and because you haven't been providing revision dates or,
any
explanation to
the nature of what you just said on on the design plan. So that's,
confusing to me at least. So what you're saying is the map that we see on the screen, which it's still dated the latest
is August 2, but it was actually since then is
those
design
to be considered
for the
rather an alternate design that the applicant
that correct?
>> Megan, I I lost the last half of what you were saying.
I'm sorry.
I'm
>> also only picking up bits and pieces of what you're saying, Megan.
>> I'll give me one second.
I'm always not my friend.
Apparently, don't have self-service in the town community room,
and the Internet reception is poor. So I'm gonna do my best.
So
I think we're confused
by this site plan. And I just want to make sure that we're clear. So what I was asking is, is this plan, the one that's it's dated 08/02/2020
as the latest revision, but it was actually revised more recently than that. It has the house rotated 90 degrees. That's an
alternative
in
wetlands
language. That's an alternative applicant considered and subsequently rejected?
Correct.
Okay. And can you
explain the reasons for rejection?
>> Yeah.
They didn't feel like a a garage forward
situation like that and turned at the strange angle that it is
and having the driveway where it is with the proposed septic system in a less desirable location,
the whole thing didn't work for them. And they felt that if that was all they could do with that particular lot, that it would not be worth the continued
efforts to have it approved. They didn't wanna build that house.
>> And I'm gonna close this
version
and go back.
I
believe that might be this one. Let me check.
This is
the original
site plan dated 08/02/2020
that I think was the most recent version of the design that the applicant is proposing.
Is this correct? Yes.
With one This is the design that the commission will consider.
No? I
>> add
one more caveat to this, though. If I might,
I would prefer that we switch the primary and reserve septic systems.
I don't think that will have any impact at all on the wetlands, and it will be a far better
septic system design.
>> Does that bring us back to the initial plan you submitted?
>> Well the initial plan I submitted was the one that we'd most like to have enacted.
Yes.
>> That's my question. So
I'm gonna go to the initial plan submitted.
We can only approve a plan.
We
need to be clear on which one it is we're considering.
>> I would like the very first plan that was submitted
to be acted on, the one that
mister Elliott was going to act on on the June 1.
>> Okay. You keep bringing that up. The the fact of the matter is that motion was not acted on.
That's correct. So
we're going to proceed with tonight's question.
>> Excuse me. Again, with reference to the documents that we have on file,
the description of the first plan doesn't really help. I need a document number. I need some kind of identification
so that I can pull up that file without having to grope all over.
There you go.
>> Okay, this is the screen sharing file.
Talk career supplemental
information.
>> This is the original
map that was submitted with the application.
It does not address any comments submitted subsequently
by either engineer Hanfield or
Mr. Gruner as it was received prior to those comments.
And this is the
design that you'd like the commission to
>> This is. Now, again,
if the commission feels that it's most important to to move the house a few feet further to the Southwest or move something a couple of feet,
then I don't have a problem with that. But this is the most
appropriate
layout for this house on this lot.
And and this is this is what my clients would like to have approved. There really
should be no reason not to approve this.
Because we're in the
we're in the Uplander area being
asked to do.
I'm sorry. Was that a question?
>> No. You started speaking, and I was giving you a chance to speak.
>> Because this is in the Upland Review area, we can always
review area and then
commissioner perhaps
>> Commissioner Larson could speak to the concerns that he brought up last time on this plan, the first plan submitted.
>> So the it and I was gonna ask Jerry, help
me understand
why
this diagram with the septic layout
is preferable in your mind to the one that puts the actual septic system outside the upland review area?
>> Because
of these because of the slope of the land,
Jed,
towards the towards the center of this property where the where the property where the new property line would be is a very flat area. And as we approach the wetlands, it gets steeper and steeper.
The Connecticut Health Code
requires that there be a minimum
leaching system spread,
and that is calculated based on the depth of decent soil and the slope of the land. So as the land slopes greater and greater, the smaller the system can be
as far as the length.
The soils are better and the slope is better towards test pit numbers number c, TPC.
So that's the area that we would like to have the septic system because it's the most appropriate for a septic system.
We're still more than 50 feet from the wetlands,
and and it should be fine, and there should be no contamination to the wetlands from that system.
Also, we'll keep the driveway on the uphill side of it so that any compaction of soils won't interfere with the septic system.
>> Okay and to
me that sounds reasonable.
I'm not a soil scientist,
a civil engineer, or any of those
kind of things, but we did have
both
an outside engineer
and we've got Hank Gruner that submitted
letters
recommending
that, you know, they both
suggested putting the
septic system outside the 100 foot
and rotating
the house. That's
what I was looking for was for a discussion on that.
And at this point,
because the second
submission
had the septic tank swapped,
that was consistent with our engineer's recommendation.
And so
he hasn't
I don't know that we've gotten the opportunity to
have him listen to the discussion on,
is
it okay in his mind? He recommended moving it outside
100 foot.
I would have thought that he would consider
all the same information that you're you're telling us tonight on the soils and slopes
and and all that kind of stuff.
>> I'm well, I'm sure that he didn't
look to design the septic system. And if he had, then he would have made a mention of the of the min minimum leaching system spread calculation,
and that's that's one of the aspects of this. The other thing is that he was asked to look at what could be done to stay out of the you know, what could be done to minimize
those things, you know, stay out of the 100 foot setback,
and you can do that. And and I've shown that. You can stay out of the 100 foot setback area,
but it's not the appropriate use of this land. It's not the best use of this land.
And
what we have shown
is
can
be done without an impact to the wetlands,
in my opinion.
And
and I think it should be your opinion too, to be honest with you.
And this should be approved conditional on the septic system being no greater than
or no closer than 57 feet to the wetlands and that the house should be no greater no closer than 75 feet to wetlands.
And if it needs to be moved another five or 10 feet, then you say, you know, 85 feet from wetlands.
But
to require them Unfortunately
>> Okay. Sorry. I'm gonna ask you to to hold on for a second.
Unfortunately,
engineer
Hanfield is not on the call this evening, so we can't ask for his input at the moment.
But I believe based on
the last letter he submitted
was based on
most recent site plan submitted, which we did not understand was an alternative that was rejected.
I'm pulling that up now.
Unclear to me whether this letter
is addressing the original version or the revised version.
Gonna ask
mister Bruner is on the line this evening, however, so I'm gonna ask him
to speak. We did have a a most recent letter from him, the the dated August 31 letter.
And I'm going to ask him to
submit comments to the commission as to how his opinion has changed, if at all,
based on tonight's discussion that the plan to be considered as the original plan, the most recent one that was submitted.
>> Are you on the line? Yes, I am. Can you hear me?
Can everybody guess? Go ahead. I can hear you.
>> Great. Yeah,
from my perspective,
it doesn't really change much regarding my recommendations associated
with
the driveway
and the, you know, vegetation
along the edge of the fence line in the wetland.
You know the issue
is I think during
pre construction and during construction it's easy to handle the soil erosion control is as Mr. Hanfield also mentioned
my original concerns were one of you know the state the condition is left after
when you have more impervious service with a driveway there you have more lawn you have
you know a portion of the house and the recommendations
I had were for how to mitigate against that. So
what I put in the updated what letter that I submitted today
was that,
you know, to include a gravel driveway rather than a paved driveway
to minimize impervious surface
in either of the configurations
to maintain
a 25 foot strip of unmoan or annually mown
land that would extend from
the fence line area out,
where that's obviously that's only feasible once you get to a part where it's you can gain the 25 feet because the driveway comes in pretty tight to the wetland immediately adjacent at the entrance, but the goal of that is to provide
a level of vegetation that that is more absorptive,
it's not forested there, you do have a tree line but the goal is to rather than having lawn right up to the tree line, try to buffer that with some thicker vegetation that gives you a little bit more buffering capacity
for the wetland corridor there. So those are really the two key pieces regardless of whether the house was within the
100 foot zone or kicked out of the 100 foot zone. Obviously having it kicked out is helpful and that it reduces
disturbance within that area which serves as a
know, a buffer but you know the gaining you know the amount of distance
there is to me is more minimal as long as best management practices are followed. I
am a little I am not an engineer, so I can't speak highly about the septic,
but that is something I think that
to be considered because that is fairly close to a wetland system
and
septic systems. Well, they're
good. Not necessarily catch everything
and you know that should be looked at carefully.
From an ecological
standpoint,
I don't necessarily see a huge issue because as I mentioned in my first
report
that the value of this system is less, there's not a lot of standing water they're serving as
breeding sites for any species of amphibians or fish or any of the wildlife like that. It's more of a corridor, it's more of an intermittent
drainage swale that basically
serves as an ecological corridor. So I'm actually less concerned about inputs that would affect any breeding populations that might be there.
So, you
know, I think there's more flexibility for consideration, given the lower ecological
value. My
main concern is really more trying to
mitigate
some of those potential impacts by increasing the buffering
potential through vegetation as well as through
preventing,
you know, more more pavement in the area because it's also a fairly impacted system with a roadway that's already there is surrounded by residential development. So avoiding any additional impacts, I think would be very helpful.
Alternative that might be considered also is to plant some some low shrubs or some denser shrub growth along the
perimeter of the driveway to provide a little bit more structure that can also be visually aesthetic and pleasing to the applicant, I would think. And that could also be a way to sort of help out with some of the buffering capacity.
So I my opinion from an ecological perspective, it would be really looking again at the septic and giving more consideration to that as long as the applicant was
willing to consider some of these best management approaches to the driveway and to the you know vegetation maintenance on that side of the
lot.
>> Thank you Mr. Krueger. Can you clarify the commission for the commission?
Do you feel that the design presented on screen, the original design submitted
is
likely
to
physically impact
the wetlands?
>> Yes, as I said in my letter that I submitted
today,
whenever you develop it's pretty well documented that development
within
100 feet actually it can be as close as 150 feet depending on the type of type of development type of activity. There's various factors, but If
you look at a lot of recommendations, a lot of reasons why
towns have 100 foot setback areas or review areas is because the literature supports that there's
activity within that zone
typically can have impacts on the wetland system. So
I believe that there would be some
impacts to the physical characteristics
likely through runoff associated with the driveway
use of fertilizers on lawns, things like that. Those are the typical things additional nutrients
that also gets into what the septic impacts can be because you can get some nitrogen input or
various inputs that can come through the septic systems and including
chemicals that
are disposed of you know pharmaceuticals and so forth.
But that has to be weighed within consideration of
you know looking at the soils and looking at the slopes and looking at a variety of characteristics.
I think it's easy
in in in
a number of cases, it's you can use best management practices to start to mitigate some of that, which is why despite the fact I felt that there were likely to be impacts associated with development
within the
100 foot zone that there were some mitigative measures that could be taken to lessen those impacts.
Does the commission have any questions for Mr. Brunner?
Smith has no questions.
Alexey, no questions.
>> Again, I have a question regarding
Hanfield's
letter,
which I'm trying to pull up here,
to the effect that
essentially
no impact,
>> no adverse Sorry to interrupt. Is it the one dated
Is it the 08/31/2001?
That's right.
>> Did you have a question George?
Didn't hear a question, sorry.
>> Okay it says
here that
it is my opinion that the proposed plan will not result in adverse or significant impact to the inland wetlands and watercourses,
presuming the conditions that follow.
So
the
question in my mind is
which
preliminary
plan exactly
is he referring to here?
As far as I can tell, his letter
does
refer
to
the plan
that
engineer Hardisty would like
us to approve
as part of the that that is the basis for the application.
>> I agree with you.
As I read the letter
it seems to reference
the initial
site plan submitted that was labeled preliminary on the bottom and dated only August
with no revisions.
So
yes.
Okay. Any additional discussion
by the commission?
Any questions of either
mister Bruner or
engineer Hardesty?
>> No, I think the original plan was is the most appropriate plan, the most
beneficial use of this plan. I think it can be
>> I think the house and septic system as shown can be constructed with Mister Hardisty, I I understand. I'm I'm giving the commission a chance to ask questions or or discuss. Yep. Okay.
If you have new information to add, I'd be happy
with that. But otherwise, just please refrain from it.
Smith has no questions.
Larson has no questions.
I
>> don't see no questions. Thank you. Agent Wagner, anything additional to add?
No.
>> Megan, would it be appropriate
to ask Kevin
if he has any comments? I'm not sure he's still on the line,
but he's
faithfully attended every one of our sessions without having the opportunity to say anything.
>> I am blanking on his last name. If you can assist me with that, that would be
did someone say it?
Arneson. Okay.
>> Thank you. I believe you're referring to the
adjacent neighbor. Arneson. Thank you. I see him on line. I'm gonna mister Arneson.
And he did it himself. Sorry about that.
Ahead. Would you like to
add any comment for the commission to consider before it possibly makes a decision on this application?
>> I don't. I will have questions for the
planning and zoning commission but nothing that applies to the wetlands commission.
The only thing was just the septic being within the 100 foot up on review area.
>> What about it? Do you have a question or statement related to it? No. I'm I mean, it it's clearly shown on the plan.
>> Everything's defined.
So, I I really don't I don't have any questions at this time.
>> Thank you.
I'm
going to open the floor for discussion and if there's no further discussion I would entertain a motion.
>> This is Jed. And I guess I would ask Jerry if his client would
still consider building the property if we asked him to put the septic
outside the 100 foot upland review area.
>> I don't see Jerry in front of his screen. I'm not sure if he left the room for a moment.
Oh, he's back.
Can you repeat your question, Jeff? I don't know
>> the answer to that, to be honest with you, Jed. I really don't.
Moving the septic system outside of the 100 foot
buffer is going to require a bigger system,
and I
don't see it operating as well.
I don't know the answer to that.
I really don't.
Okay.
>> And I didn't have any other questions. Do feel ready to make a decision on this application?
Thank you.
So
I will add to the conversation if it's relevant.
One minute,
Mr. Chairman Elliott. So we did
speak to our special lanes
about
this application as well as others.
And he
us
that in order to
request alternative
to be considered and I might not be paraphrasing exactly correctly
but you need to have reason to believe that there's an impact from the a physical impact to the wetland of the current design.
I have not seen
any information presented
that would demonstrate
the current
system
is likely to have a physical impact on the wetland. Any of the other commissioners feel like speak up at this point?
Vice Chairman Elliott, did you have a comment to add or a question? I was wondering if we were ready to entertain a motion.
I'm ready.
>> Okay. I would move to approve the application
with standard
conditions
and with
let's see how to phrase it. I would like to see
the
recommendations
by Mr. Gruner
included in the conditions
of the permit.
Do I have a second for the motion?
Ed Smith seconds the motion made by George Elliott.
Thank you. I'll open the floor to discussion.
>> How is he? I just had a concern as to how we would structure
an approval
that would raise
Hank Kruger's recommendation
as opposed to just a blanket
reference to his letter.
You
said that the maintenance of a.
Appreciate it. I'm just wondering how
and this came up before at a previous meeting.
You know, indicated
it was simply a your recommendation.
I'm wondering if
if that would be the extent of it.
Or whether we would have something added to the plan that would be
just part of the site plan
and enforced as such.
>> Do any other commissioners have So Commissioner Smith, I would say that we just use those three bullet points as far as the
adjustments.
>> I think I'll just point out I believe the third bullet is is
addressed by our standard conditions.
So it would really be the, the first two bullets that would be
additions to the special conditions of the permit if the commission says.
>> Megan, this is
Go ahead, Angel. The
last one
said
look on the paper.
That the other wetland on the other side of the property should be protected with
sediment and erosion control fencing. It doesn't have a bullet point, but it looks like it should.
It's the last
>> Is that you I'm sorry. Would that be a recommendation that you would include?
>> That would be part of his recommendations. There would be the three bullet points, and then there was another one on page two that doesn't have a bullet point, but it looks like it's a separate recommendation.
I remember talking about it with Hank.
So I think I would add those four as conditions.
Megan, did you want me to address that?
This is Hank. Oh, absolutely. Yeah.
>> Yeah. The reason I didn't bullet that was because the first three bullets were really associated with the wetland system there on the east that drainage and that was a separate one.
And I believe Megan is correct that the bullet I included the third bullet,
Installing
sediment erosion control barriers is definitely caught by the basic
regulations and also,
know, is is already planned. I just wanted to reiterate that so it really be those first two bullets regarding that wetland on the East and then as Joe was mentioning
and in abundance of caution I saw that
although it was noted that due to the topography
it was highly unlikely that runoff would be going toward the small wetland depressions.
I thought it would be good to just out of abundance of caution to encircle
those with some or at least on the disturbance
side with some sediment fencing.
>> You.
Agent Wagner, are there any additional special conditions that you would recommend the Commission consider as part of a permanent approval?
Nothing I can think of.
>> This is Jed. I'd like to ask Hank one more time to just make clear to me his initial letter
that recommended
the septic outside the 100 foot.
He had some
he had some concerns
about that
and why he wanted it outside the 100 foot upland review.
He is okay with the
with us putting he is okay with
Jerry's rationale for why we would put it inside the Upland Review area?
>> I
actually
don't believe
that I addressed the septic
in my initial review.
I think that came up. I
did not. I talked about pushing the house
reconfiguring
the housing lot.
James
That position in the house and the and then the issues of the buffering capacity I dealt with. James
The,
I mean, I think the septic system. You
know, that's a I mean, that's really a big engineering question. From
an ecological standpoint,
I didn't feel because I did not see anything that was a vernal pool or held water that would likely support breeding
populations of amphibians or fish or invertebrates that you
know I wasn't really as much worried about
septic inputs or or heavily worried about.
You know the proximity. I wanted to try to mitigate as much as possible was the goal that I put in there.
Given the value that I had assigned to the system based on its ecological functions. So I didn't really get into the septic system at all. Did not, I did not pull that out and call that out. I really dealt with the housing location more from an impervious surface standpoint,
as well as the driveway and the the
revegetation.
Okay, thank you, Hank. Yep.
>> Mr. Gurners, your recommendation,
let's see, you had noted a recommendation to maintain a gravel rather than a paved driveway. Is the intention of that recommendation
basically to improve the perviousness of the driveway and therefore
would other
materials
other than gravel
be part of your recommendation,
for example, pervious pavement or things like that, the applicant options? Sure, yeah, that's
>> exactly what the recommendation is for is to eliminate
a paved surface that has high runoff so
pervious pavers would be fine,
gravel driveway would be fine, there's various ways that
techniques that could be used for that certainly. The goal is to try to just avoid the
impervious surface.
>> Halsey,
I believe that the intent of the boat
was to comply with the fire marshal with
provide a turnaround.
>> Is this the bump out we're referring to?
Okay, thank you.
>> Yeah, and then simply the recommendation I had with that was once again just trying to reduce
Joe and I had talked about this just trying to reduce the
amount of impervious surface, but if it's you know essential for safety obviously that trumps.
>> Mr. Hardisty, can you answer that question whether the bump out is a requirement to meet fire marshal recommendations or requirements?
>> It's more of a requirement to be able to turn a car around.
But that, you know, that includes,
emergency access vehicles as well.
>> Could the bump out be located on the far the other side?
>> As
far as I'm concerned, it could be. Yes. I don't think that there's any restrictions as to proximity to the property line as long as we don't go over it.
So, yeah, if that's
if if that's
that big of an issue then I'm sure we can work around it.
>> Well, aesthetically, it would
would look better to the to the wet,
but now it's closer to that those wetlands. Right?
I am not qualified to talk about aesthetics.
I think that's beyond the scope of our discussion.
>> I would agree with that statement.
And I think it's a valid point that moving the bump outs to the other side of the driveway would
is it further from the wetlands that have been the primary focus of our discussion, but it would place it closer to the other wetlands on the property.
So the commission should consider that as well.
So there's a motion on the floor made by George Elliott, Vice Chairman Elliott to move to approve the application. It was seconded by Ed Smith. The original motion was to approve with the standard conditions and with those
of Mr. Rooner
as outlined, let's see, in his, I believe, August 31 letter.
There any additional discussion?
Any
modifications to the motion or should we move to vote? Can we take that
>> as
the
recommendations
as they have evolved
as our discussion?
That is to say, than eliminate the bump out, we could say modify the bump out to reduce
proximity
to the wetlands,
maintain the 25 strip.
As you said, the
sediment and erosion controls are part of standard conditions,
so they're not additional conditions.
And then finally,
providing sediment and erosion control
for
the wetland
depressions to the west side of the parcel. So we have three
conditions
under discussion
that are not part of the standard conditions.
>> Any comments from the commission response to Vice Chairman Elliott?
The only other
modification
to the motion I would recommend would be
clarifying that it's a two year permit as opposed to a longer duration permit.
And that it applies to the site plan presented.
I was concerned by I think it may have been captured in the last meeting motions
discussion that
the site plan was intended to represent a worst case scenario and
left to infer that the
site plan could change.
If that's the case, if the site plan changes,
>> this is really a statement directed at the applicant and their agent. If the site plan changes,
perhaps through planning and zoning approval,
or otherwise a modification
would need to be submitted to wetlands
for permit approval. So the permit applies only to the site plan as presented.
Okay. So I will paraphrase.
The motion on the floor is to approve the application
as presented in the initial site plan labeled preliminary.
Was motion was made by Vice Chairman Elliott, seconded by Chairman Smith.
Conditions are to apply as well as the following special conditions
as noted in the August 31 letter by Mr. Bruner
and modified by the commission's discussion. So
essentially,
the bump out be redesigned
to be located further away from the primary wetlands,
the driveway surface be a
more pervious surface than asphalt options
include but are not limited to gravel,
And that a 25 foot strip of vegetation is maintained
out from the existing tree fence line.
And the permanent duration is two years.
Believe does everyone any
comment before we move forward is that motion clear ish to everyone.
I will entertain
entertain I'll call for a vote
at this time, then on the motion so Vice Chairman Elliot, how do you vote.
Aye.
Commissioner
halsy.
Aye.
>> Commissioner Larson.
Commissioner Smith? Aye.
And Chairman Lele, I vote aye as well. So the motion carries five zero zero.
Wagner,
if you can
work to
put the public notice out to allow for the two week
public notice period and then draft
a permit associated with this application. So the permit would be valid two weeks from this evening and then two years after that.
Okay.
>> Mister Hardisty, did you have any questions of the commission before we move on to the next agenda item?
No.
>> Okay. So then,
please be in touch with agent Wagner,
and follow-up accordingly.
Okay.
We'll move on to the next agenda item, which is item 4B,
application IWWC
20 dash 23 presented
by William and Donna Phillips for activity at 57 Hendy Road, a new residential construction in an upland review area, which includes modification of a flood a floodplain.
And I'm going to close out the items from the previous application.
Application materials.
I'm gonna ask, same as for the last application,
if agent Wagner can walk us through
the new application materials that have been submitted.
>> Alright.
We have
a letter from August 24 from
Brandon Anfield
reviewing
the current plan
revised
through
August 12,
and then he reviewed
the engineer Andrew Bushnell's response
too. And then
there was a letter
from Brandon Hanfield, August 31. That was where
he reviewed the current proposed plan and
stated his opinion on it.
Then there was also on my screen.
>> That's the letter from
my conversation with Brandon because the
applicant
wanted a
clarification
on
the term flood prone district. So I sent him
her email and asked him for comments, and his comments are included in that in that email in that letter.
>> Is
plan the most recent plan? I have the most recent revision date is August 12.
Correct.
>> Thank
you.
So I did deliver because this is a big project.
Just to be out there, aware I did deliver
full size plans to
missioners.
I personally just happened to
the small screen approach.
So the exception
of,
I believe,
these last two letters that came in recently,
the commissioners were provided with hard copies of the rest of the application material.
I will open the floor to I believe I see the applicant and
the applicant's engineer,
Mr. Krishnell, on the call this evening. So I'll open the floor to discussion by the commission.
And then,
agent Wagner, did you prepare any materials this evening for the commission to consider in relation to this application?
No, I didn't.
>> Do you have any recommendations for the commission to consider in relation to this application?
Nothing that I can think of.
>> You feel that
all of the
information requested by the commission, mister Gruner,
and engineer Hanfield has been received at this time?
>> I
didn't get a letter from Mr. Gruner.
Don't think.
On the call?
>> I am.
Would you like me to address that Megan?
>> Yes. And if you can specifically address any
expected physical impacts
to the wetland or watercourses,
and then your subsequent
recommendations,
>> if any, to mitigate those impacts. Okay. Doctor. Yeah. And the reason I didn't submit a letter I can give you, you know, because really my thinking is not there's really nothing that's changed on my recommendations from the first report. And,
you know, quite frankly, one of the challenges with this that I was wrestling back and forth with is,
as I stated in my original report.
Don't see any direct impacts to
the
system
associated
with that would affect the ecology of it. With
the construction of the house and the site preparation work.
Only exception to that which is being discussed by the engineer is the, you know, the balancing of cuts and fills where there's a proposal to remove some
fill from
part of the floodplain areas part of a balance. But
I don't believe that would have a significant ecological impact on the ecosystem there or the species that are
that are there.
My only recommendation that I provided in there was really to provide exclusion fencing
around the areas where there would be construction work.
Especially if activity was going to occur during the activity season of the wood turtles, which are state listed species that were noted on the site plans through the NDDB review. That
would prevent those
animals from moving into any of the areas and potentially being injured or killed. But
the real, the real I spent some significant time in the original report I did. Steve Addressing something that to a large extent is actually somewhat beyond the purview of the wetland
And that's really the activities,
the ongoing activities that will occur within the
floodplain area. And
the reason I did that is I wanted to get on the record
some recommendations
that hopefully the applicants would consider. Steve
Sort of best management practices and I presented them in a bit of a hierarchy. So from ideal to, you know, no real disturbance in a floodplain area to Steve
You know, other activities that are current, some of which are currently occurring in that floodplain area where there's some mode walkway strips and there's some access areas and in the past. I know there's been some gardening and so forth. Steve
And provided recommendations on how to continue with those activities Harper without impacting
the wood turtle populations. They're having an inordinate impact on the Steve Ecosystem
functions,
but from a regulatory standpoint as far as how the wetland commission could act on that. That's where the challenge becomes because it really they don't really have a physical
they don't really change the physical characteristics or have a an impact on the wetland per se.
So
I was wrestling with how to best present that and I chose to present it in that first report. If
this was a larger subdivision, it could easily be dealt with through planning and zoning and conservation easement areas and recommendations.
But this is not so
I offer those up really as an opportunity to
for the for the applicant to
consider
uses of that floodplain
area associated with the parcel.
If that makes sense to everybody.
>> The Commission have any questions
or
response to Mr. Greer's comment? Okay
hearing none,
does either the applicant or their representative engineer Bushnell wish to provide any additional information about the application for the commission to consider?
And engineer Bushnell, you are muted. Sorry.
>> Just to
be clear,
Brandon Hanfield's last memo was was dated what? August.
>> It was August
31.
Oh, okay. I don't have a It wasn't it's it's not posted. I got it really late today.
>> Oh, okay. Alright. Okay. Okay. Can you email that to me and I can post it? Did you email it to me? Yeah.
Email it to the commission.
>> I'm gonna open this at the risk of is this it?
Yeah. It's it.
>> Okay. So it is
in mister Hanfield's opinion, the proposed plan will not result in adverse or significant impacts to inland lands or watercourses. From the engineering perspective,
he does not expect,
significant impacts.
Perfect.
You're welcome.
I'm assuming you don't disagree.
No. No.
>> I believe the
applicants are on the line. Do they wanna add anything further or address mister Gruner's comments or anything of that nature before the Commission proceeds there? It is not required.
No,
we don't have anything else to add Megan.
>> I will open the floor back up to discussion by the Commission then
and if there's no discussion we'll move on to entertaining a vote if someone wishes to make one.
Not hearing any discussion. Would anyone like to make a motion?
>> Yeah. Halsey.
I could move to approve the application
of
William and Donna Phillips
referencing the
most current map
Plan which is
appears to be revised through 08/12.
Is that correct, engineer Bushnell?
Yes.
Thank you.
>> I'm sorry it's dated fiveonetwenty
twenty revised
through
eighttwelvetwenty
twenty.
>> Do I have a second for the motion? It's Smith seconds.
Okay. The motions made by Commissioner Hallisey, seconded by Commissioner
Smith. As
presented,
referencing
updated
May first
and August 20.
And I open the floor just
Okay. Hearing none, I will ask a question of agent Wagner. Do you have any special permit conditions that you would recommend the commission consider for this application?
No.
>> Megan, this is Linda.
Is this
motion
include
just regular conditions?
>> Policy,
would you like to respond to that?
Standard conditions?
>> Conditions, yes.
Also,
Lyndon, can you read me the data on the plan that you referenced?
>> I cannot see it, I don't have it. I think it's this one.
>> Okay, it's fiveone, I thought I said, I think I might've said fivetwelve
when I made the motion.
The date on the plan is, original date is 05/01. You had the right dates, Jim. It okay.
I'm sorry.
Propose that the standard conditions be attached.
Be part of the motion. Part of the approval.
>> I'm just flipping back
to mister
wonder if I can find
it.
Mr.
Gruener's recommendations regarding
exclusion fencing and timing of the activities.
I would also recommend that the motion restricts
the permit to a two year duration.
Any additional comments, discussion, questions?
Linda, do I need to formally motion to revise the motion to include the two things I noted? Yes.
Thank you. Okay. So I will motion to revise Commissioner Hallisey's original motion
to include a permit duration of two years and the recommendations
of Mr. Gruner regarding the timing of activities and exclusion fencing around.
>> I will second the motion to amend
the primary motion.
>> Vice Chairman, any discussion?
Okay, hearing none, I'm gonna call for a motion to amend the motion. So we'll do roll call. Vice Chairman Elliott.
I vote aye.
Thank you. Commissioner Hallisey. Aye.
Commissioner Larson?
Aye.
Commissioner Smith?
>> Chairman Molley votes aye as well. So the motion to amend the primary motion carries five zero zero.
So back to the primary motion. Any additional discussion before we vote?
Okay.
Hearing none, I will do a roll call vote. Vice Chairman Elliott?
Aye.
Commissioner Hallisey?
Aye. Commissioner
Larson?
Aye.
>> Commissioner Smith? Aye.
And Vice Chairman Lally votes aye as well. So the motion carries five zero zero. The application is approved with the standard and special conditions noted.
Agent Wagner, can you please work
with,
the building department to issue the public notice
and to draft the permit?
Okay.
>> Alright. I believe that concludes
the special meeting. So, as a reminder, our next meeting is Tuesday, September 15. I am not sure. I was trying to share meetings with someone and
don't go by the town calendar online. I the last time I checked, it wasn't accurate.
So I'm expecting to meet Tuesday, September 15 at 7PM.
That's what I had on the master calendar due to the Labor Day holiday.
Hopefully, everyone has it on their calendars. And
with that, I will entertain well, I'm sorry, I should back up. So
I apologize. I offered the previous applicant a chance to ask questions before we moved on. Do the applicant or engineer Bushnell have any questions or comments before we conclude their item?
I don't hear any. I'm not sure if
engineer Bushnell is on the line, but, agent Wagner, if you can make sure to follow-up directly with him and the applicants regarding the application.
Okay.
>> So with that, I will entertain a motion to adjourn.
Move to adjourn.
>> Motion
to adjourn made by Vice Chairman Elliott at 08:18.
Any second? Seconded
>> Commissioner Hallisey. We'll do a roll call vote. Vice Chairman Elliott?
Aye.
Commissioner Halicy?
Commissioner Larson?
Aye.
>> Commissioner Smith? Aye.
And Chairman Lele votes aye as well. So the motion carries five zero zero. The meeting is adjourned at 08:18PM.
Not at all.
>> Linda do you have everything you need for the minutes?
Hope so.
I
>> just want to make a note that I don't think the community room is the best place to Zoom from.
I learned
>> No kidding. A lot of your conversation was really garbled.
>> Oh, yeah. Yeah. I apologize.
The alternative is a house with a two and a five year old crying on me. So
I'll look for option c.
Not specific